hello there mr. Rubin all right JP
January 1 we got anything good for the
people well I don't know how good it is
I guess we're gonna find out how good it
is it's not something I'm thrilled about
by any stretch of the imagination so you
and I have been talking for a couple of
weeks now
ever since this scandal around carl
benjamin or sargon of akkad broken we
decided a while back that we were going
to well do a variety of things right we
were going to announce our departure
from patreon which is what we're doing
in this video I'm going to leave patreon
January 15th I also am going to leave
patreon On January 15th which by the way
we should just be clear this is not
something that we wanted to do we were
both perfectly happy on patreon patreon
at least for me it's been the backbone
of my show I mean that's somewhere
between 60 and 70 percent of our funding
is through patreon so this is not
something we wanted to do I know we're
gonna talk about a whole bunch of things
in this recording but that New York
Times article that came out the
implication was oh we're doing this for
money it's like we're taking a major hit
right now and opening ourselves up to
all sorts of risks so I'm going ahead
and doing that because I believe we can
do something better we've got to figure
out exactly what that is and that's what
we're working on so we can say two
things I mean I I'd also like to thank
the patreon people for what they did in
the past because they provided me with a
tremendous amount of or the ability the
opportunity to generate a tremendous
amount of financial support at a time I
really needed it and so I'm not happy in
the least with what has happened I have
thought about it a lot and believe that
given patrons proclivity to censor and
the reasons that they're doing it
especially as I've looked more and more
deeply into the reasons particularly
with regards to my discovery of the
website changed the terms I've become
increasingly convinced that it's
unethical to continue my association
with the company and I also agree jack
conte said
New York Times article trying to justify
say Sam Harris's departure and our
threatened departure that it was
motivated primarily by financial gain
and like look I've got nothing against
financial gain you know I've said that
from the beginning I and if if things
that I'm doing generate an honest amount
of money that I can put to reasonable
use then so much the better
but if this is a major financial blow
I'm using the patreon money for a
variety of reasons most particularly to
support this educational endeavor that
I've talked to people about right our
attempt to build an online education
system and so like it's a major hit yeah
and of course you know just to be clear
it's like when we're doing my show I
mean I don't have to tell everybody
about YouTube be monetization but for
example in my show a week or two ago
with Imam to Edie was demonetized by the
algorithm then demonetised
further after manual review by a human
so it's patreon it's it's the supporters
the individual people that allow us to
go ahead and do more of these
controversial so to speak episodes so
yeah just nothing that we're doing right
now is against the people that have
supported us or our patrons or anything
like that so this is about making a
stand against this ever moving
encroachment on free speech on free
expression and the rest of it and it's
like this is one that we just feel is
the right one to make the move on and
the reason we jointly decided on January
15th while there was a couple of reasons
the first was that we thought that we
might have something approximating an
alternative potentially available for
preliminary launch of that date although
we've decided to delay that because the
user interface needs work because that's
the other thing right is that there
needs perhaps to be a replacement for
patreon if that's a possibility like
it's not obvious to me that corporations
can run platforms for untrammeled
communication successfully on the net in
today's climate yeah would anything I
might design but let's not let's not
gloss over that I mean it might be
possible that the patreon method is not
what's needed exactly for the future of
the Internet I mean this is what we're
trying to figure out right now which is
why we've got every engineer I mean
people from Google and Facebook and
Yahoo
everybody reaching out to us because
it's like everyone's trying to solve
this problem and it's still I mean one
of the things we've been talking about
now for the last well it's really for
the last year but in intensely in the
last month is what actually is the
problem itself because until we really
figure out what the problem is well I
think I think the problem is how to
regulate an incredibly diverse range of
opinions
if such regulation needs to be
instantiated we could take a limit case
for example the desire of companies like
Facebook not to have their platforms
used for recruitment for Isis it's hard
to make a case that that's not a
reasonable restriction right but then
but then the next issue is I think you
could make an exception there because
maybe you consider that a wartime
exception or something like that but
then the fundamental problem to me seems
to be and I'll return again to that
change the terms website that a whole
variety of companies and organizations
spearheaded in not least by the Southern
Poverty Law Center that hateful
organization yeah the worth that has
decided that they're going to compel
encourage what the fame perhaps
companies that don't band together to
regulate what they see as hate speech
yeah and this is where well this is
where the moving line is the key part of
this because you can always find the
frit the most fringe cases you can
always find Isis on one side and you
know the most fringe KKK white
supremacist group or whatever you want
to call it on the other side but let's
not forget Southern Poverty Law Center
they've written things about you they've
written things about me ayaan Hirsi Ali
and Maajid Nawaz and Sam Harrison sorry
and a litany of Majin sued them too
and actually won so there there is a
pushback but this is just another level
of the stand it's like they cannot be
trusted
to be on the boards of any of these
organizations that are deciding what
terms
yeah but they are should have access
it's really who should have access to
the Internet
no it's worse than that Dave because
when they start to pressure the credit
card companies and I would consider this
a warning to everyone who's listening is
like okay let's think this through so
the New York Times last week wrote an
article about the credit cards
complicity in loaning money to that
terrible tiny minority of people who
engaged in mass shootings right stating
that it was the responsibility of the
credit card companies to monitor and
potentially prevent that activities like
okay so what's this what's the idea here
the idea is that the companies to whom
we have entrusted our monetary system in
large parts that would be the credit
card companies now get to review our
spending patterns to determine if what
we purchase is in accordance with that
with what they regard is morally
acceptable okay and and we think that's
a good idea
now that's where we're headed and and
MasterCard and Visa and PayPal are
already starting to block people like
they brought MasterCard was instrumental
in blocking Spencer Robert Spencer right
its Robert Spencer or not Richard
Spencer yes its best-selling author and
the guy who runs jihad wash MasterCard
required patreon 2d platform him and
just to be very clear they sent out a
tweet which everyone can find I'm
shocked that they haven't deleted it yet
where they said that they and they use
this word which i think is the key to
the whole thing they said that they
unfortunately had to delete his patreon
because of MasterCard so what are they
actually saying there are these patreon
saying oh we didn't want to delete your
page but MasterCard forced our hand I
mean that is some deeply scary stuff
yeah well and we have to talk about hate
speech because you know I think the
whole concept of look obviously there is
people can be very nasty when they
communicate but the idea that there's an
identifiable category and you can put
boundaries around it and terment hate
speech and then you can produce
committees or deal with people on a
one-to-one basis as patreon is doing
without any central
policy or let's say despite their
central policy or that you could turn
that into an algorithm that could
validly identify hate speech without
producing false positives right without
accusing people who shouldn't be accused
of violating all of that's just
completely it's just Baker's the
imagination as far of course and you're
also just opening a Pandora's box from
Hell because just in the last couple
days I don't know if you saw this but
the women's March in California canceled
their rally because they felt that it
was too white yeah now imagine if they
canceled their rally because it was too
black or to anything else it's like so
does that now count as hey are you guys
now being racist against white people no
no that that wouldn't be a problem
for these guys one of the things that I
can't fathom in some sense is the lack
of imagination on the part of the people
who are engaging in censorship of what
they regard as hate speech like there's
an old military adage which is that if
you invent a weapon it will be used by
your enemy within 15 years okay so why
what makes the people who on the on the
left because they're the ones who are
doing this well as you can clearly see
in the change the terms website what
makes them so sure that exactly the same
tactics won't be used against them like
at the drop of a hat once once the
tactics have been validated and put in
place I think it's either it's either
just very short sightedness on their
hand or they think that they can
actually stamp out enough hate within
that very small window before it would
turn on them or they just don't think
these things fully through but yeah yeah
or or there's another there's another
possibility too which is that they're so
opposed to the fundamental structures of
the West that let's say and regard them
as so patriarchal impressive that they'd
be willing to take the risk of
sacrificing their own free speech just
to have their what have their
destructive way something like that
we should also acknowledge that in the
the New York Times piece that was
written which was written by Nellie
Bowles who wrote the now infamous piece
about you and enforcement ah gimme that
the quote that jacqueline Hart who is
the head of trust and safety over a
patreon the core there's no hidden who
is no grounding in Soul
koffie or any of the background training
that might be necessary to even remotely
begin to participate properly in such a
thing no of course not quite so the
quote that she gave Nellie in the
article said that you can't say these
wob loosely quoting this now you can't
say these words on our platform
referring Carl referring to him saying
the n-word in that video yeah which we
know they were using out of context and
all that but he never said it on their
platform he never said it on patreon he
didn't even say it on his own channel
that was you know using patreon for the
funding so there was a it's almost the
entire story was built on quicksand that
he that tried to put out there on the
New York Times now of course myself and
many other people tweet the hell out of
it and gets hundreds and thousands
probably of retweets and comments to
Nellie and and she doesn't respond nor
does the New York Times issue any sort
of correction about the most fundamental
piece of the story was a lie
and I don't have a don't have a problem
doing that so that's why this is so
layered about speech and finance and
journal is so amazing to see journalists
take the journal if one of the things
that happened in Canada to me was that
you know after I made the initial videos
that cause such a political furor was
that once the main journalists in Canada
sort of figured out what I was doing
they all came out my support
like the post media group which is 200
newspapers all came out to support what
I was doing because they realized that
oh they're journalists apart from
comedians there isn't anybody who relies
more on the principle of free speech to
justify and allow their occupation even
to exist for the New York Times not to
understand that this threat is also a
threat to everything upon which their
entire organization has been predicated
is also an indication of that same kind
of willful blindness that we've already
been discussing but having said that I
would still like to say that I think the
biggest danger here I really and it it's
just made my jaw drop over the last
couple of weeks thinking about it is the
fact that the credit card companies are
now taking it upon themselves to
potentially please
the activities of their users it's like
my god is that really I just I just
can't believe that we any sensible
person would think that through and then
want to live in a society where your
spending habits are being monitored by
the company that basically produces your
money yeah well think of anything more
totalitarian than that so loosely quote
our friend Eric Weinstein should
republicans be allowed to use roads that
that's sort of where we're headed here
that every public good will be
eventually decided can access to it will
you have access to water it should
should an avowed white supremacist right
now that is potentially watching this or
lives in America somewhere but one of
the 42 of them should should they have
access to water at their home should
they allowed to be a get electricity at
their home or phone lines or all of
these things I mean this is where we're
headed especially when you ever expand
the definition of hey that person is
they won't in China right you know
that's where they're going right so is
that the test case well it I think it's
it's an indication that the fact that
the Chinese have been tempted into this
is also an indication of the temptation
that's intrinsic in the technological
power the credit card companies are in a
weird situation as far as I'm concerned
because the only reason they work at all
is because people actually trust them
completely remains like oh you're just a
proxy for money like you're a proxy for
cash in fact that's basically how good
MasterCard advertises itself right so
you're a proxy for cash and the
government doesn't watch what you spend
your money on except in extraordinary
extraordinary limited cases I mean their
money laundering laws and so forth but
that's a direct violation of a law right
that's part of tracking down criminal
activity now it has nothing to do so far
with with hate speech which by the way
is protected by the First Amendment yeah
so or which means in some sense that it
doesn't exist you know as as illegal as
a legal concept right now this is like
which is right we shouldn't go us over
that fact to because you know Jordan we
just did however many countries in in
Europe and we're gonna go back this
spring and it's like everybody that we
met was jealous of the freedoms that we
have in the United States relative to
speech you know I mean everybody that
would come up to us after the show holy
cow I wish we could say that and I wish
we didn't worry about this or that or
jokes or the rest of it we did that
video in Oslo where you talked about
Angela and it's like they're jealous of
our freedom so we should be very clear
here they though you're right because we
now have a payment processor issue which
is in indirect connection to whatever it
is that we're trying to build out here
and we're still it's a little Amorphis
at the moment yeah that it's changing
because a lot of people are saying all
right you guys really want to solve this
then you have to go full critical yeah
the promo video has to be hosted crypto
yeah the finances have to be hosted or
have to be done via crypto yeah all
these things these are these are major
major things that we're trying to figure
out on every front certain payment
processors are a little more willing to
stand up to the mob than others so have
different people I mean really going on
every front hair that's right well the
tentative platform that we're trying to
build and to build carefully will
provide the possibility of multiple
payment portals in the hope that the
creators will be less susceptible to
being rapidly shut down or perhaps shut
down at all but you know you only a fool
would say that that problem is going to
be definitively solved I have some real
and increasing sympathy for the
cryptocurrency types you know but the
problem there is that as far as I can
tell their solution is still
sufficiently technically complex to keep
it out of the mainstream use and also
not sufficiently liquid to actually
constitute a realistic current
replacement even for credit cards right
so one of the things we've been
discussing is that it's almost like we
have to have several markers down the
road to figure out what the real
solution is because not everything can
be solved in terms of
terms of service tomorrow related to
everyone that exists not everything can
be solved tomorrow related to the
payment processors maybe crypto really
is the ultimate answer but it's not the
answer tomorrow for everything so we're
really we're plotting out a lot here but
it seems like a fresh and sort of
fitting way to start the year I think so
and so for January 15th I mean part of
the reason that we picked that date as I
said before it was because we thought we
might have something to announce with
regards to an alternative platform but
you know saner heads have prevailed in
that commerce yeah yeah yeah and also we
wanted to give people an opportunity to
decide what they wanted to do without
just springing it on them I mean I have
some real admiration for Harris for
acting so immediately and definitively
yeah and it's funny you know I saw some
criticism it's like all right well Sam
dropped immediately and look you and
Peter said you're still there and you're
talking about this whole thing and it's
like we all have different things to
consider we all have different family
situations different business situations
different livelihood situations
everything so it's like we were really
trying to just plot this thing out
properly and and to be very clear we're
still in the process of that yeah so for
any of surf for anyone watching this
right now if you're supporting Jordan on
on patreon or you're supporting me on
patreon or both of us or whatever it is
it's like now we're trying to shift
people because at least by getting off
patreon at the moment we've removed one
of the middlemen and you can now go
directly go to directly to Jordan B
Peterson comm or Dave Rubin comm and you
can at least if you want to donate you
can do that for now while we figure out
everything else and that way we've
removed one of the pieces here because
there's just too many pieces here that
that are creating this mess I think it's
too much to hope for a perfect solution
to a very complex problem and we're
muddling through the best we can and
hopefully people will regard our
decision joint decision to leave patreon
as a step in the right direction however
imperfectly taken yeah well look I think
I said it before but I
really think that and maybe this will be
the defining idea of 2019 is that I
think we're basically at the point where
people have to decide what sort of
internet they want yeah and it's not
only what sort of internet it's really
what sort of freedom do you want in a
digital world and either or do you want
any or do you want any and maybe maybe
you don't or you don't want to think
about it and you just want to play for
at night and watch porn and never think
it through
but assuming that you'll be allowed to
watch porn right for that now you really
are tight or play for that matter right
so the games of violence should be
allowed what makes you think that credit
card companies should allow you to use
their there are funds to purchase first
shoot first-person shooter games for
example or or any game where anyone is
killed no no you're totally right that's
it I mean that sounds completely
dystopian and yet it seems like that
would just be the next encroachment that
we would see here so the point at the
end at the end of this is I think
everyone for 2019 since it's the first
day of a year it's like you have to
think about what type of internet do you
want what type of ability to communicate
with other people do you want and if you
want something that's a little better
than what we've got right now we better
stand up quick because this window we
know it's closing slowly but we never
know when it's gonna really slap shot
quick so so we're working on it and and
I think people are ready to stand up
with us I really do we might also
suggest to people and this is of course
up to everyone who's viewing this to
decide but you know a couple of them
thousand letters to MasterCard and
PayPal and Visa indicating pronounced
displeasure at their plans to become
custodians of the monetary supply for
ethical reasons might also be in order
you know these companies are responsive
to public pressure which is perhaps
partly why they're determining to play
the role of censor to begin with you
know they're they are facing pressure
from these let's call them activists
interest groups who again are outlined
on change the terms on the website
change the terms and they're responding
to public
pressure and to sum it that's
understandable it's understandable but
but inexcusable it's uncertain in a
certain regard but the right way perhaps
to begin to push back is to let the
credit card companies know that there's
our constituency on the other side that
Isis all right
suspect constitutes the vast majority of
credit card users the silent middle
majority of let's say Western society
who were neither radically right nor at
eclis left who would just as soon not
have their spending habits monitored by
giant corporations nobody to that the
left is so opposed to corporate entities
you know on principle especially the
sizable ones and you know have a certain
justification for being skeptical about
the moral direction of very large
organizations are so eager to hand over
the reins of social control to precisely
the companies you'd think they would be
least likely to crawl into bed with I
mean really mastercard visa it's like
right or at the same time they'll they
want to hand over more control to the
government to handle these things and
and we should be pretty clear that in
the last couple weeks that we've been
discussing this every single discussion
that we've had about this
I don't think once did we entertain the
idea of oh we've got to get the
government involved to fix this thing I
mean there there could be as you as you
referenced earlier there could be
specific legal issues that pop up
related to collusion and a couple other
things cartel develop - yeah like that
sort of thing yeah but but the beauty of
this and again why I'm sowing some
watching my my monthly rev up my company
go down even though we're making some of
it back but as I'm watching that happen
as I said to you last time
I'm incredibly inspired right now
because literally thousands of emails
are pouring in from people that want to
work with us that want to help us that
want to figure out how to fund things or
that want to work as engineers or the
rest of it and that tells you that that
people are people are afraid and they
see this problem and they just want some
solutions and and maybe there isn't any
solution as you said I've also been
talking with you online with a whole
bunch of the people who've been loosely
aggregated under the aegis of the
intellectual dark web and and that's
probably 30 people that that we've been
communicating with with a variety of
peripheral people and it's also useful
to let people know that every one of
those people is unbelievably concerned
about what happened to Carl Benjamin two
circuits are going and even more so
dumbstruck by the collusion of the
payment processing companies and and the
emergence of this activist
infrastructure online that's devoted
specifically to the suppression of free
speech yeah well and also we should also
note that within that group of say 30 or
some odd people we all sort of look we
agree on basic fundamental principles
related to free speech and things like
that but there's a lot of disagreement
on how to move forward with this I mean
we're talking it out respectfully as we
always do but some people are saying
stay and fight on patreon because this
is how you know they're small enough say
that you might get them to change some
people are saying you gotta go and some
people are saying some version of you
know mixing those two and nobody's clear
about the proper pathway forward yeah
but that's again I mean I think this is
what the brilliance of human ingenuity
is all about it's like well there are
gonna be some pitfalls in front of us
and stain would have its risks and
leaving would have its risks and we're
all gonna do what we think is why we've
already discussed about two writers then
there's a there's no there's no no risk
option here and like and so we're taking
the risk of leaving and then we're gonna
make the best of it I mean often when
you take a risk you often in life all
you have is a choice between two
different risks and sometimes neither of
them are risks you would like to take
but then in the aftermath of the
decision a new field of possibilities
opened up in front of you - and whether
or not you made the right decision is
actually a consequence of how well you
manage the aftermath of the decision so
we'll we'll keep talking over the next
couple of
like I've got good people working on
this alternative you know which which
was as I mentioned in other places
started seven months ago or so and good
people supervising it whether it'll turn
out to be a viable product and whether
or not we can figure out how to
implement it in a sustainable way that
actually addresses these issues in a
reasonable manner remains to be seen
yeah hey on a personal note just because
you know I got to see you a couple days
before Christmas in West Palm Beach and
and we had dinner with with your family
and your kids and everything hasn't it
sort of been nice because I I did a week
with with my brother and sister and
nieces and nephews over Christmas also
sort of circling back to family on some
of this it's given me a lot of
perspective you know it is mean because
I'm getting I'm getting reached out by
so many different people on all
different fronts but then to have sort
of a close-knit group of people that
really do have your interests in mind
and all those things you know there's
family with your kids at dinner it was
like oh these are good people too
well there's unanimity on the part of
the people around me that the proper
thing to do is well twofold one is to
separate myself from patreon in
accordance with our discussions and the
second is to proceed with exceeding
caution and non over promise or try to
deliver too quickly a solution although
to work on that carefully so that's what
we've decided to do yeah so let's just
be crystal clear on that latter part we
are working on this we're gonna be
deliberate we're gonna be cautious we
understand that it can't be solved
tomorrow we understand that there's a
financial part a free-speech part and
everything else and we're just gonna lay
these things out in front of us and
we're gonna keep working through them
with a lot of the people that you guys
know and trust yeah and and and with
with some other people and hearing from
random people that have given us ideas I
mean I've been forward and you emails
left and right where people are like you
know this might be the the pressure
point you might want to go after so
we're just gonna keep going yeah yeah
okay well I got a couple of things to
end this I guess let's summarize and
then I've got a couple of things just to
let people know about sure
ah well the first is so we're both
leaving on January 15th and the second
is we're working on this platform and
the third is a warning to people to keep
a close eye on what the credit card
companies are up to because that's a
really bad thing in my estimation I
guess that's probably it on my front I
have a talk coming up in Zurich I have a
couple of talks in California in January
yeah I'll be with you on those yep and
the tickets to those are available on my
website at Jordan beat Peterson com the
final thing is I also set up with my
partners as a New Year's token let's say
that future authoring program from the
self authoring suite mm-hmm we put it up
at 50% off with the code NY 2019 and so
if anybody's out there wants to make
some personal what do you call those
resolutions for the new year again this
program is an ideal way of doing that
and so that's also partly a thank you to
everyone who has been so supportive and
interested in the last year and so I
think that's basically I think that's
basically that what do you all right no
I think that's basically it so I'll just
quickly you know give a shout out to
Dave Rubin calm slash donate and what
we're what we're trying to do and I know
you're trying to do this as well is that
for whoever signs up now and we're
taking its one time and monthly
donations that you can do there are
going to be ways that we think once we
build out whatever it is we're working
on that that it'll all be able to be
flipped into that so it's not like we're
gonna have people constantly having to
start new accounts or you know sign up
for new things or anything like that
we're trying to make this as easy as
possible for everybody look there's
gonna be some bumps but this is it
that's one to say about 2019 there's
gonna be there's gonna be some bumps
well I don't know if you know this
Jordan but we got an American election
come in the year after that so
okay mr. Rubin happy new year
alright Happy New Year brother healthy
and in Cali in a couple weeks
bye for now